<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>special-districts on Christopher B. Goodman, PhD</title>
    <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/categories/special-districts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in special-districts on Christopher B. Goodman, PhD</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 16:23:44 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.cgoodman.com/categories/special-districts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Florida is dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, home of Disney World. What happens next is anyone’s guess.</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/04/28/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world.-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess./</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 16:23:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/04/28/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world.-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a blog post for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/&#34;&gt;London School of Economic’s US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;. It covers a recent controversy about the Reedy Creek Improvement District &amp;ndash; something I have a somewhat unique perspective on as a scholar of local governments and, in particular, special districts. See below for the full text of the post as well as a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess&#34;&gt;Florida is dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, home of Disney World. What happens next is anyone’s guess.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/2022/04/27/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess/&#34;&gt;LSE US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following criticism from the Disney company over a controversial education bill, last week Florida&amp;rsquo;s Governor, Ron DeSantis signed legislation which would dissolve the Reedy Creek Improvement District, the location of the company&amp;rsquo;s Disney World Resort. &lt;strong&gt;Chris Goodman&lt;/strong&gt; explains the history of the special district, how it has functioned, and the uncertainty around what may happen next.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 22, Florida Governor Ron DeSantis &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sun-sentinel.com/news/politics/os-ne-disney-reedy-creek-bill-signed-20220422-3ijuuhs5wra6vcbmy4qhpqp6gy-story.html&#34;&gt;signed legislation&lt;/a&gt;, dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, effective June 1, 2023, apparently in reaction to the Disney corporation’s opposition to the state’s recently enacted Parental Rights in Education bill, which limits classroom instruction on gender identity and sexual orientation. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/travel/2022/04/22/florida-disney-reedy-creek-desantis/&#34;&gt;politics of this action notwithstanding&lt;/a&gt;, what exactly is going on and who is involved? What is the Reedy Creek Improvement District, and why does it matter that it’s being dissolved? Welcome to the shadowy world of special districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s back up. In the United States, there are five main forms of local government. The first three are cities, counties, and in 27 states, town or townships are general purpose local governments. They provide many services, tax residents and levy fees, and issue debt to support infrastructure. They’re often the local governments that people identify with. The fourth are school districts. Finally, we have special districts. Typically, these local governments provide a single service to a fixed geographic area. They often have the power to tax (mostly property tax but sometimes other taxes too) or levy fees for services (like transit fares or water fees). Some special districts have the power to issue debt. The Reedy Creek Improvement District (RCID) in central Florida, and home to the Walt Disney World Resort, falls in this camp; however, in 1967 the state endowed the RCID with many more powers, powers generally associated with a city or county. These services are to the benefit of landholders, primarily the Disney Corporation and its subsidiaries, and are largely paid for by taxes and utility fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blogsmedia.lse.ac.uk/blogs.dir/58/files/2022/04/New-blog-image-test-3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Credit: Asher Heimermann, CC BY-SA 4.0, via Wikimedia Commons&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Credit: Asher Heimermann, CC BY-SA 4.0, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is responsible for services such as environmental planning, water control, roadway maintenance, emergency services, and water, sewer, and electrical utilities. If you think that these sound like many of the services a city provides, you would be correct. These services are supported by property taxes and utilities fees levied on the landowners inside the RCID. In effect, Disney taxes or charges itself to provide services it values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is like another kind of special district in Florida, the Community Development District (CDD). CDDs exist primarily to facilitate the issuing of bonds to fund infrastructure development in new residential developments. They allow housing developers to put in roads, water pipes, sewer lines, and other things, pay for them with debt, and pay the debt off by charging an additional property tax to new homeowners. Rather than increase the purchase price of new housing, CDDs allow the cost of necessary infrastructure to be spread over time. CDDs differ from the RCID in a few important ways. CDDs are more limited in their ability to provide public services, and importantly, CDDs have a completely different governance structure. CDD’s governing board members are initially allocated by the amount of land an owner has in the district. As the primarily landowner, this is the developer. As homes are sold, board seats convert to popular election until the entire governing board comprises popularly elected members. The RCID is different in that landowners always control the board seats. As such, the Disney Corporation and its subsidiaries control the decisions made about service delivery and infrastructure within the district.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-next-for-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district&#34;&gt;What next for the Reedy Creek Improvement District?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is dissolving in 2023. What now? The answer to this question is unclear. The legislation inserts a single paragraph into the Florida statutes and does little to explain how the dissolution will occur or what happens during the process. Undoubtedly, the law will be subject to litigation; however, the RCID, like all special districts in Florida, is subject to the &lt;em&gt;The Uniform Special Districts Accountability Act&lt;/em&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leg.state.fl.us/statutes/index.cfm?App_mode=Display_Statute&amp;amp;Search_String=&amp;amp;URL=0100-0199/0189/Sections/0189.072.html&#34;&gt;outlines&lt;/a&gt; how independent special districts dissolve. This law specifies the debt and assets of a dissolving special district be transferred to a local general-purpose government, who assumes responsibility for paying off the debts and/or continuing to provide services. This likely means Orange (and possibly Osceola) County will have some responsibility for the transferred debt and assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the tax levy that supports the RCID is also eliminated upon dissolution. Currently, the RCID taxes itself about double the average property rate of Orange County, FL. If Orange County assumes the debt, assets, and service delivery requirements of the RCID, it must do so with its own (lower) property tax levy. This could mean taxpayers county-wide will foot the bill in the form of future tax increases, or it might not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little about the process is known. Many of the actors in the process of dissolution have yet to be assigned their roles. The uncertainty of the process is the issue. If an implementation plan accompanied the dissolution, the responsible parties could react and plan for what happens on June 1, 2023. Right now, we’re left with many questions and few answers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special Districts: America’s Shadow Governments</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/22/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 10:09:40 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/22/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a short blog post for the UIC &lt;a href=&#34;https://gfrc.uic.edu&#34;&gt;Government Finance Research Center&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; blog. The piece is a bit of a short explainer on special districts in the United States and a few fiscal issues that arise. It&amp;rsquo;s by no means comprehensive but part of a broader focus I have on writing more popular or policy focused work on these relatively hidden local governments. Below is the intro (I don&amp;rsquo;t have full re-print rights) and a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-districts-americas-shadow-governments&#34;&gt;Special Districts: America’s Shadow Governments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I teach about the property tax at Northern Illinois University, I play a game with my public administration graduate students. I ask the homeowners in the class to dig out their property tax bill and share it with the class. We go line by line looking at the millage rates of each levy and examine who is doing the levying. Some, like the county, the city/village or the school district(s) are easy to identify. But other line items are somewhat more obscure, like mosquito abatement districts, conservation districts, civic center authorities, joint water authorities and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This naturally leads to conversations about why these specific services are provided by a special district rather than a general government and whether this arrangement leads to higher taxes. We discuss whether, if there was a different vehicle for funding these services, property taxes might go down. In my state of Illinois, home to the largest number of independent local governments in the country, this is a particularly important question. But like many questions like this, there are no easy answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the rest on &lt;a href=&#34;https://gfrc.uic.edu/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/&#34;&gt;GFRC&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium on Special District Management</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/10/03/symposium-on-special-district-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 14:47:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/10/03/symposium-on-special-district-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paq.spaef.org&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public Administration Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is seeking papers for a symposium on special district management, edited by myself and Alex Henderson at Marist. You can find the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/paq-cfp-2020.pdf&#34;&gt;full CfP&lt;/a&gt; below. Abstracts are due on &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;. Selected manuscripts are due for peer review on May 1, 2021 and &lt;em&gt;PAQ&lt;/em&gt; expects publication in late 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;symposium-overview&#34;&gt;Symposium Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special districts are a profoundly important form of government, having experienced significant growth of the last several decades (U.S. Census Bureau, 2019). Though generally receiving less attention then general local governments, including cities, towns, townships, or villages, special districts are often charged with providing core public services that impact the day-to-day lives of citizens (Foster, 1997). These services include common functions like education, fire protection and emergency medical services, and library, water, and sewer services. Special districts are unique in their single functional focus, potentially complex and overlapping geographical boundaries that may not be conterminous with other units of local government (Bollens, 1957), and in the churning that comes through special district creation and dissolution (Goodman &amp;amp; Leland, 2012). Despite the growth and prevalence of special districts, our knowledge of these units of government is still relatively limited (Goodman &amp;amp; Leland, 2019), and additional attention to the management, functions, and contexts of special districts will add to the growing body of information on these important service providers. This symposium will provide a venue for conceptual or empirical research that examines issues related to the management of special districts. Topics may include, but are not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Management of special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design and implementation of best / better practices related to managing special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Special district size, function, and interrelationships with local demographic, socioeconomic, or economic contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency and accountability in special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance measurement, program evaluation, and values of efficiency, effectiveness, or equity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geography, local government capacity, and special district functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fragmentation among units of local government and service efficiency and effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other topics as related to independent or dependent (subordinate) special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;proposal-submission-process-and-timeline&#34;&gt;Proposal Submission Process and Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area of inquiry is necessarily interdisciplinary, and proposals from a variety of fields and specializations are encouraged. These may include those that focus on public management, urban planning, urban affairs, economics, and others. A 500-word proposal should be submitted via email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:alexander.henderson@marist.edu&#34;&gt;alexander.henderson@marist.edu&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposals should include information on the purpose or aim of the article, a discussion of the methods or approach used, and a discussion of the fit with the symposium topic. Please also include author name(s), affiliation(s), and full contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposal acceptance will be sent by December 1, 2020. Full manuscripts will be due by May 1, 2021 for peer review. Final decision on manuscript acceptance is anticipated by November 1, 2021, with publication in late 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CfP (PDF)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/paq-cfp-2020.pdf&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CfP (Google Drive)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1oHpDOBsEe4lbXWZwpysCi3mvTMdDBERx/view&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bollens, J. C. (1957). &lt;em&gt;Special district governments in the United States.&lt;/em&gt; Berkeley: University of California Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foster, K. A. (1997). &lt;em&gt;The political economy of special-purpose government.&lt;/em&gt; Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodman, C. B., &amp;amp; Leland, S. M. (2019). Do cities and counties attempt to circumvent changes in their autonomy by creating special districts?. &lt;em&gt;The American Review of Public Administration&lt;/em&gt;, 49(2), 203-217.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodman, C. B., &amp;amp; Leland, S. M. (2012). Cost shocks and their relationship to the creation, consolidation and dissolution of US local governments. &lt;em&gt;Public Finance and Management&lt;/em&gt;, 13, 58-79.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. Census Bureau. (2019). &lt;em&gt;2017 census of governments, individual state descriptions.&lt;/em&gt; Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How a type of local government you may have never heard of may be costing you a bit more</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2019/03/20/how-a-type-of-local-government-you-may-have-never-heard-of-may-be-costing-you-a-bit-more/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2019 17:18:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2019/03/20/how-a-type-of-local-government-you-may-have-never-heard-of-may-be-costing-you-a-bit-more/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a blog post for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/&#34;&gt;London School of Economic&amp;rsquo;s US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;. It covers a recent publication in &lt;a href=&#34;http://slg.sagepub.com/&#34;&gt;State and Local Government Review&lt;/a&gt; on the implications of overlapping local governments on local public employment in the US. You can find more information about this piece &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/research/jurisdictional-overlap/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. See below for the full text of the post as well as a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-a-type-of-local-government-you-may-have-never-heard-of-may-be-costing-you-a-bit-more&#34;&gt;How a type of local government you may have never heard of may be costing you a bit more&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/2019/03/04/how-a-type-of-local-government-you-may-have-never-heard-of-may-be-costing-you-a-bit-more/&#34;&gt;LSE US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special districts are one of the most common forms of local government in the US. Aimed at tackling a specific issue in a certain area, these districts can often overlap with city and county governments. In new research Christopher Goodman looks at whether this overlap can mean an over-provision of public employees. He finds that while this overlap can often lead to a small increase in the number of public employees, the effect is much greater on local revenues – i.e. taxes – which can be up to ten percent greater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special districts are a unique and very popular form of local government in the United States. They can overlap any other forms of local government such as cities or counties, take on nearly any geographic shape, and provide public services similar to cities. This arrangement creates the potential for the over-provision of public services due to a lack of coordination between numerous overlapping governments. This has been found to be the case with &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1540-5907.2008.00344.x&#34;&gt;local government revenues&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1091142114545678&#34;&gt;public debt&lt;/a&gt;, but the question remains if this over-provision extends to local government’s most common cost, employees. In general, the answer is yes, but the size of the “overlap effect” is quite small.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special districts are the &lt;a href=&#34;https://factfinder.census.gov/bkmk/table/1.0/en/COG/2012/ORG02.US01&#34;&gt;single most numerous&lt;/a&gt; form of local government in the US as of 2012. Their unique attributes make them attractive for solving all manner of local issues. Need to run a metro-wide transit agency? A special district fits the bill. Need to provide a particular public service to a particular neighborhood? A special district works here too. This flexibility allows areas to tailor the collection of public services they receive to fit their needs. There are of course those who think this kind of fragmentation of public service provision is bad and can lead to all kinds of ill effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back the original claim. Why would the lack of coordination among many special districts lead to an over-provision of public services? Ideally, it wouldn’t; however, we do not live in an ideal world. The single service nature of many special districts is the source of the problem. Most special districts have one job to do: provide the service they were created to provide. This naturally leads elected officials and public managers to want to do that job more and better. Potentially so much more than it becomes more than what would ordinarily be provided. If the various services provided by a collection of special districts were instead provided by a single city government, all those services (likely organized into departments) would have to compete with each other in the annual budget process for funds. This competition would keep things in line. Because each service is provided by (and funded by revenues from) a separate and autonomous special district, there is no budget competition and the potential for over-provision is born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note what I just described requires no one, elected or appointed officials, public managers, or voters, to do anything wrong. All that is required is for those groups to do what they normally do. Elected officials favor policies that will get them reelected. And it’s likely those same elected officials are at least somewhat interested in the public service the district provides. Both are completely rational, but also likely result in more public goods or services being provided than would be in a city government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most local government services are highly labor intensive; therefore, if there is an over-provision problem, it should show up in more local public employees than would ordinarily be employed. This is accomplished by comparing the level of local public employment across all types of local governments in areas with high number of special districts per city such as St. Louis City, Missouri to areas with low special districts per city like Baltimore City, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, these areas may employ more or less public workers for reasons other than special district overlap such as the prevailing wage (local governments tend to hire fewer workers when wages are high), revenues from state or federal government (local governments often hire more workers when someone else is partially paying for them), or the wealth of the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I examine this relationship in all county areas in the United States from 1972 to 2012. On average, a county has about 40 full time equivalent local public employees per 1,000 residents and roughly 2 special districts per city. Overall, the results of the statistical modeling suggest there is an upward bias in the number of local public employees in areas with more special district overlap, the size of the effect is quite small. Moving from the 25th percentile of overlap (0.5 special districts per city) to the 75th percentile (2.3 special districts per city) increases in level of local public employment by about one percent or less than one full time equivalent employee. When compared to the overlap effect of local revenues (approximately a 10 percent increase), these findings appear quite small indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blogsmedia.lse.ac.uk/blogs.dir/58/files/2019/03/New-blog-image-test-3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;LSE&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s generally thought that competition between many local governments is a means to constrain inefficient behaviors of those governments. However, this theory was built on competition between horizontally arranged local governments (e.g. cities); governments that do not overlap one another. While informative, most of the growth in US local governments over the last 50 years has been in the vertical direction by numerous overlapping special districts. This is a fundamentally different arrangement where it appears the competitive forces that constrain cities do not apply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the “overlap effect” does not appear to be particularly large for local public employment, it is for other local outcomes (revenues, specifically). This disconnect begs the question if these two results are truly the state of US local governance, where are the excess tax dollars being spent? The results of my research suggest not on employees (at least not directly) so there’s more of the puzzle to be completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is based on the paper, “&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0160323X18774402&#34;&gt;Jurisdictional Overlap and the Size of the Local Public Workforce&lt;/a&gt;” in State and Local Government Review.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special District Creation and Dissolution</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2018/06/30/special-district-creation-and-dissolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jun 2018 16:53:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2018/06/30/special-district-creation-and-dissolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;files/misc/spdist.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Special district creation and dissolution by year.&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Special district creation and dissolution by year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
