<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
      <title>Blog on cgoodman.com </title>
    <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
    <rights>Copyright (c) Christopher B. Goodman.</rights>
    <updated>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 14:27:51 -0600</updated>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illinois Special Districts Per Capita, 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2023/01/25/illinois-special-districts-per-capita-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 14:27:51 -0600</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2023/01/25/illinois-special-districts-per-capita-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;files/misc/il-cog-17-pcspdist.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;IL special districts per capita.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Illinois independent special districts per 10,000 residents, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Florida is dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, home of Disney World. What happens next is anyone’s guess.</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/04/28/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world.-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess./</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2022 16:23:44 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/04/28/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world.-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a blog post for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/&#34;&gt;London School of Economic’s US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;. It covers a recent controversy about the Reedy Creek Improvement District &amp;ndash; something I have a somewhat unique perspective on as a scholar of local governments and, in particular, special districts. See below for the full text of the post as well as a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess&#34;&gt;Florida is dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, home of Disney World. What happens next is anyone’s guess.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/2022/04/27/florida-is-dissolving-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district-home-of-disney-world-what-happens-next-is-anyones-guess/&#34;&gt;LSE US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Following criticism from the Disney company over a controversial education bill, last week Florida&amp;rsquo;s Governor, Ron DeSantis signed legislation which would dissolve the Reedy Creek Improvement District, the location of the company&amp;rsquo;s Disney World Resort. &lt;strong&gt;Chris Goodman&lt;/strong&gt; explains the history of the special district, how it has functioned, and the uncertainty around what may happen next.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 22, Florida Governor Ron DeSantis &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sun-sentinel.com/news/politics/os-ne-disney-reedy-creek-bill-signed-20220422-3ijuuhs5wra6vcbmy4qhpqp6gy-story.html&#34;&gt;signed legislation&lt;/a&gt;, dissolving the Reedy Creek Improvement District, effective June 1, 2023, apparently in reaction to the Disney corporation’s opposition to the state’s recently enacted Parental Rights in Education bill, which limits classroom instruction on gender identity and sexual orientation. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.washingtonpost.com/travel/2022/04/22/florida-disney-reedy-creek-desantis/&#34;&gt;politics of this action notwithstanding&lt;/a&gt;, what exactly is going on and who is involved? What is the Reedy Creek Improvement District, and why does it matter that it’s being dissolved? Welcome to the shadowy world of special districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s back up. In the United States, there are five main forms of local government. The first three are cities, counties, and in 27 states, town or townships are general purpose local governments. They provide many services, tax residents and levy fees, and issue debt to support infrastructure. They’re often the local governments that people identify with. The fourth are school districts. Finally, we have special districts. Typically, these local governments provide a single service to a fixed geographic area. They often have the power to tax (mostly property tax but sometimes other taxes too) or levy fees for services (like transit fares or water fees). Some special districts have the power to issue debt. The Reedy Creek Improvement District (RCID) in central Florida, and home to the Walt Disney World Resort, falls in this camp; however, in 1967 the state endowed the RCID with many more powers, powers generally associated with a city or county. These services are to the benefit of landholders, primarily the Disney Corporation and its subsidiaries, and are largely paid for by taxes and utility fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://blogsmedia.lse.ac.uk/blogs.dir/58/files/2022/04/New-blog-image-test-3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Credit: Asher Heimermann, CC BY-SA 4.0, via Wikimedia Commons&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Credit: Asher Heimermann, CC BY-SA 4.0, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is responsible for services such as environmental planning, water control, roadway maintenance, emergency services, and water, sewer, and electrical utilities. If you think that these sound like many of the services a city provides, you would be correct. These services are supported by property taxes and utilities fees levied on the landowners inside the RCID. In effect, Disney taxes or charges itself to provide services it values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is like another kind of special district in Florida, the Community Development District (CDD). CDDs exist primarily to facilitate the issuing of bonds to fund infrastructure development in new residential developments. They allow housing developers to put in roads, water pipes, sewer lines, and other things, pay for them with debt, and pay the debt off by charging an additional property tax to new homeowners. Rather than increase the purchase price of new housing, CDDs allow the cost of necessary infrastructure to be spread over time. CDDs differ from the RCID in a few important ways. CDDs are more limited in their ability to provide public services, and importantly, CDDs have a completely different governance structure. CDD’s governing board members are initially allocated by the amount of land an owner has in the district. As the primarily landowner, this is the developer. As homes are sold, board seats convert to popular election until the entire governing board comprises popularly elected members. The RCID is different in that landowners always control the board seats. As such, the Disney Corporation and its subsidiaries control the decisions made about service delivery and infrastructure within the district.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-next-for-the-reedy-creek-improvement-district&#34;&gt;What next for the Reedy Creek Improvement District?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RCID is dissolving in 2023. What now? The answer to this question is unclear. The legislation inserts a single paragraph into the Florida statutes and does little to explain how the dissolution will occur or what happens during the process. Undoubtedly, the law will be subject to litigation; however, the RCID, like all special districts in Florida, is subject to the &lt;em&gt;The Uniform Special Districts Accountability Act&lt;/em&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leg.state.fl.us/statutes/index.cfm?App_mode=Display_Statute&amp;amp;Search_String=&amp;amp;URL=0100-0199/0189/Sections/0189.072.html&#34;&gt;outlines&lt;/a&gt; how independent special districts dissolve. This law specifies the debt and assets of a dissolving special district be transferred to a local general-purpose government, who assumes responsibility for paying off the debts and/or continuing to provide services. This likely means Orange (and possibly Osceola) County will have some responsibility for the transferred debt and assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the tax levy that supports the RCID is also eliminated upon dissolution. Currently, the RCID taxes itself about double the average property rate of Orange County, FL. If Orange County assumes the debt, assets, and service delivery requirements of the RCID, it must do so with its own (lower) property tax levy. This could mean taxpayers county-wide will foot the bill in the form of future tax increases, or it might not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Little about the process is known. Many of the actors in the process of dissolution have yet to be assigned their roles. The uncertainty of the process is the issue. If an implementation plan accompanied the dissolution, the responsible parties could react and plan for what happens on June 1, 2023. Right now, we’re left with many questions and few answers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Horizontal v. Vertical Fragmentation</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/01/25/horizontal-v.-vertical-fragmentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 18:24:38 -0600</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2022/01/25/horizontal-v.-vertical-fragmentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/bivariate.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Bivariate Map of Horizontal and Vertical Fragmentation in the U.S.&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bivariate map of county level municipalities per 10,000 residents v. special districts per 10,000 residents.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Municipal Incorporation in the US, 1789 - 2020</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/12/07/municipal-incorporation-in-the-us-1789-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 19:29:57 -0600</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/12/07/municipal-incorporation-in-the-us-1789-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/us_animated_compressed.gif&#34;
         alt=&#34;Animation of municipal incorporations in the US by year&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An easier to share version is below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J7WjPgGAnJc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The structure of US local governments is often a poor predictor of local economic growth</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/11/17/the-structure-of-us-local-governments-is-often-a-poor-predictor-of-local-economic-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 14:48:38 -0600</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/11/17/the-structure-of-us-local-governments-is-often-a-poor-predictor-of-local-economic-growth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a blog post for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/&#34;&gt;London School of Economic’s US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;. It covers a recent publication in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/loi/ujua20&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Urban Affairs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on the implications of local government structure on long-run economic growth in the US metropolitan areas. You can find more information about this piece &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/research/frag-grow/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. See below for the full text of the post as well as a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-structure-of-us-local-governments-is-often-a-poor-predictor-of-local-economic-growth&#34;&gt;The structure of US local governments is often a poor predictor of local economic growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://blogs.lse.ac.uk/usappblog/2021/11/17/the-structure-of-us-local-governments-is-often-a-poor-predictor-of-local-economic-growth/&#34;&gt;LSE US Centre Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metropolitan economic growth is a perennial topic of interest to policymakers and scholars. Why do some areas flourish while others decline? &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/0304-3932(95)01206-2&#34;&gt;Previous analyses&lt;/a&gt; suggest the underlying strength and structure of the economy is important, as is &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.regsciurbeco.2006.11.004&#34;&gt;nicer weather&lt;/a&gt;. Another important consideration is the structure of local governments in a metropolitan area. The structure and powers of local government as a source of metropolitan growth are a popular topic in more international contexts. However, they have received significantly less attention in the US. States grant considerably more powers to local governments, and local governments are typically more numerous in the US than other parts of the world, making this an interesting case to study.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-influence-of-local-governments-on-growth&#34;&gt;The influence of local governments on growth&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How might the structure of local governments influence economic growth? There are two competing schools of thought. The “polycentrists” explain that more local governments can be a means to economic growth. Many local governments in an area create a competitive environment, where each government competes to provide public services most efficiently at the lowest cost. For overlapping local governments, the geographic differences in local government size offer the opportunity to match efficient production of services more closely, i.e., take advantage of economies of scale, and allow component local governments to make decisions on the level of service provision appropriate in their area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the opposing side, the “government reformists” suggest that fewer local governments can be a means to economic growth. Efficiency forms the core of the argument; however, mechanisms are different. Rather than focusing on competition-induced efficiency, the government reformists focus on potential administrative efficiencies of having fewer local governments. Eliminating duplication of services, overcoming coordination issues, and directly realizing economics of geographic scale are all possible mechanisms to drive growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, academic research falls more often on the polycentrists side. &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jue.2004.08.002&#34;&gt;More local governments can be associated with higher growth&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1111/jors.2011.51.issue-1&#34;&gt;not&lt;/a&gt;, and city-county consolidations, a recommended government reform, &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1007/s11127-019-00699-z&#34;&gt;is generally not related to economic growth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;measuring-economic-growth-in-us-metropolitan-areas&#34;&gt;Measuring economic growth in US metropolitan areas&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In new research I analyze economic growth (population, jobs, per capita money income) from 1960 to 2000 in 314 metropolitan areas in the US. I borrow the methodology of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/0304393295012062?via%3Dihub&#34;&gt;Ed Glaeser&lt;/a&gt; of Harvard University and colleagues, where long-run economic growth is a function of the initial conditions of the metropolitan area (population, wealth, population growth, unemployment rate, manufacturing share, and percent of the population with a college degree). Those metropolitan areas with “better” initial conditions should grow more quickly in the following period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My model includes information on five variables covering local government characteristics. The first three variables are: the share of the total metropolitan population residing in central cities, the average population of suburban (non-central) cities and the share of the metropolitan population that resides in unincorporated areas. These variables measure the influence of general-purpose local governments with higher values associated with lower political fragmentation. The last two measures, the number of school districts divided by the number of non-overlapping cities/townships, and the number of special districts divided by the number of non-overlapping cities/townships, relate to the influence of special-purpose local governments. Higher levels are associated with greater political fragmentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1 shows the influence for my model’s variables with population growth as the dependent variable (results for jobs growth and income growth look similar). Of the general government structure variables, only the share of the central city population has any significant impact. Those metro areas with larger central cities relative to their suburbs declined in population on average, and the size of this effect grows as the period of growth increases. Special district overlap is a positive predictor of metropolitan growth in the longest time range as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1 – Population growth, 1960-2000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;files/misc/popgrow-coeff.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Population growth coefficients&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Population growth coefficients&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the other variables, local government structure is a poor predictor of metropolitan growth. Initial economic conditions such as prior growth or the unemployment rate are far better at predicting long-run growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking more closely at regional differences&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if the overall results are masking variations between regions? Metropolitan areas in different parts of the US grow differently, and local government structures may affect these metropolitan areas in different ways. Figure 2 examines this possibility by breaking down the sample by Census region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2 – Regional differences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;files/misc/popgrow-coeff-region.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Population growth coefficients&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Regional population growth coefficients&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 shows that some local government structure factors affect economic growth differently depending on the region the metropolitan area is in. Local government structure has little effect on growth in metropolitan areas in the Midwest; however, the structure of the suburbs and special-purpose governments is important for the northeast. Results are far more mixed for the southern and western regions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research stands at odds with much of the international literature on decentralization and economic growth that suggests increased decentralization can be a means to enhanced growth. The US is a highly decentralized country from a governance perspective. The benefits of devolution are likely already baked into the system, whereas decentralization in highly centralized countries is new and more likely to shock the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-does-all-this-mean&#34;&gt;What does all this mean?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Policymakers in the US sometimes claim that the structure of local governments is helping or hindering economic growth in their areas. Some areas are highly fragmented, and it is easy to claim this is a significant impediment (or enhancement) to growth. My results suggest a more tepid response. The structure of local governments can be important, but it is often region-specific and easily overshadowed by the underlying economic characteristics of metropolitan areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a policymaker wants to develop a strategy to enhance economic growth, there are better options than to propose a radical alteration to the existing local government structure. There is more bang for the buck in improving local educational opportunities or working to reduce unemployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article is based on the paper, “&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/07352166.2020.1742578&#34;&gt;Political Fragmentation &amp;amp; Economic Growth in US Metropolitan Areas&lt;/a&gt;” in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of Urban Affairs&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic Project Management Notion (Update)</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/07/14/academic-project-management-notion-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 15:04:45 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/07/14/academic-project-management-notion-update/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, I wrote a small post about how I use &lt;strong&gt;Notion&lt;/strong&gt; as a project management tool (the post is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/06/11/academic-project-management-using-notion/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). I didn&amp;rsquo;t really expect it to be as popular as it is, but I also didn&amp;rsquo;t expect myself to change too much about the process either. It was working. Fast forward one, sort of over, but not really pandemic later. Things have certainly changed, sort of. This post is meant to explain some of those changes and to provide a template for anyone who wants to give this a spin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if you&amp;rsquo;re just here for the template, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/cbgoodman/Manuscript-Status-32416dd541ee4b549686bbe0a7646a61&#34;&gt;here you go&lt;/a&gt;, click &amp;lsquo;duplicate&amp;rsquo; in the top right corner, sign in to Notion, and add it to your workspace. Bing, bang, done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;lets-back-up&#34;&gt;let&amp;rsquo;s back up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who may not have read the original post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-1.png&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.notion.so/educators&#34;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt; is free for educators. Just put in your .edu email address, and you&amp;rsquo;re good to go. Notion is mainly a holding area for all kinds of content, but one of its most potent tools is relational databases. We can link all sorts of data together to surface more helpful information about what we should be working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;main-project-database-reimagined&#34;&gt;main project database, reimagined&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original design of this was for a main project database. It included all kinds of information about projects, but it was mainly a spreadsheet at the end of the day. You could do similar things in nearly any spreadsheet program. The main project database still exists (named &amp;lsquo;Manuscript Status&amp;rsquo;) but is now linked to do additional databases for more functionality. Let&amp;rsquo;s jump right in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-building-blocks&#34;&gt;the building blocks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned above, the primary component of this system is the Manuscript Status database. Each entry in this database represents a single manuscript and includes a lot of metadata on each project. We&amp;rsquo;ll use that metadata on the main page to surface helpful information, but it&amp;rsquo;s also beneficial in keeping track of all kinds of relevant information specific to each project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-ms-1.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript 1&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Manuscript 1 Metadata&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As seen above, there are a few pieces of vital information (and many hidden details, click &amp;ldquo;6 more properties&amp;rdquo; to see it all). Is the project active? What is its status? This bit is linked to another database; I&amp;rsquo;ll explain more in a moment. What Journal is it current at or targeted for? Or what conference is it being submitted to?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-ms-2.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript 1 Content&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Manuscript 1 Content&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further down, this page includes all the relevant data about this manuscript. It consists of the abstract, some more metadata like information and checklists, notes about the project, and any reviewer/editor comments that might have come back. These comments are in their own database and linked, relationally, to this particular manuscript. Any comments related to this manuscript in the Manuscript Reviews database will show up in this section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-ms-3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript 1 Review&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Manuscript 1 Reviews&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This portion can be highly customized. And it&amp;rsquo;s not too dissimilar to the original database. What is vastly different is how data is surfaced on the main page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-dos&#34;&gt;To-dos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-1.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript Status, To-Do, Active&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The All Active Projects view&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A neat feature of Notion is you can display databases (a type of page) any number of times in multiple places. Each of these individual instances of a database can have its own &lt;em&gt;views&lt;/em&gt; or methods of sorting, filtering, or otherwise displaying the data. These can be pretty powerful when used effectively!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;lsquo;To-Do&amp;rsquo; panel at the top of the page is one such instance of a database (the Manuscript Status database). It shows active projects in one view (active = marked active and either in-process or R&amp;amp;R&amp;rsquo;ed), conference papers in another view, and overdue projects in a third view (those past their due dates). These views surface relevant items to work on—active projects requiring work, with near-term due dates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-3.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript Status, To-Do, Conference Papers&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The Conference Papers view&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-contextual-information&#34;&gt;more contextual information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below the to-do section is a lot of contextual information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-2.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Manuscript metadata&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the left-hand side is the Status database, showing all manuscripts in the central database. If you click on one of the boxes, it will display all the relevant manuscripts in that category. It&amp;rsquo;s an easy way to surface all of the manuscripts at one time that meets specific status criteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/notion-update-status.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;All in-process manuscripts&#34;/&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;All in-process manuscripts in the Manuscript Status database&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right-hand side lists all manuscripts in the Manuscript Status database and a view to show only published work (easy to find all in one place for annual reviews, tenure, etc.). Underneath that is where all the databases that make this entire system work live. The page is self-contained, though Notion will allow linking across heavily nested databases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;templates&#34;&gt;templates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout, there are templates for adding content. Need to add a new manuscript to the main database? Click on &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; in either instance of the Manuscript Status database on the front page and click &amp;ldquo;New Manuscript Template.&amp;rdquo; The manuscript page is pre-formatted &amp;ndash; add your content—same thing for manuscript reviews. Just click &amp;ldquo;new,&amp;rdquo; then &amp;ldquo;review template,&amp;rdquo; and add the reviews. Remember to link the reviews back to the relevant manuscript. Rinse and repeat for status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still bad at project management. These changes have helped me focus on what needs to be done. Hopefully, it&amp;rsquo;s helpful for you too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;credits&#34;&gt;Credits&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All credit for the icons used here goes to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flaticon.com/authors/smalllikeart/flat/2&#34;&gt;smalllikeart&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flaticon.com/&#34;&gt;https://www.flaticon.com/&lt;/a&gt;, a free SVG icon site. Things like this help break up the monotony of a blank white page.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special Districts: America’s Shadow Governments</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/22/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 10:09:40 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/22/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of writing a short blog post for the UIC &lt;a href=&#34;https://gfrc.uic.edu&#34;&gt;Government Finance Research Center&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; blog. The piece is a bit of a short explainer on special districts in the United States and a few fiscal issues that arise. It&amp;rsquo;s by no means comprehensive but part of a broader focus I have on writing more popular or policy focused work on these relatively hidden local governments. Below is the intro (I don&amp;rsquo;t have full re-print rights) and a link to the original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-districts-americas-shadow-governments&#34;&gt;Special Districts: America’s Shadow Governments&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I teach about the property tax at Northern Illinois University, I play a game with my public administration graduate students. I ask the homeowners in the class to dig out their property tax bill and share it with the class. We go line by line looking at the millage rates of each levy and examine who is doing the levying. Some, like the county, the city/village or the school district(s) are easy to identify. But other line items are somewhat more obscure, like mosquito abatement districts, conservation districts, civic center authorities, joint water authorities and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This naturally leads to conversations about why these specific services are provided by a special district rather than a general government and whether this arrangement leads to higher taxes. We discuss whether, if there was a different vehicle for funding these services, property taxes might go down. In my state of Illinois, home to the largest number of independent local governments in the country, this is a particularly important question. But like many questions like this, there are no easy answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the rest on &lt;a href=&#34;https://gfrc.uic.edu/special-districts-americas-shadow-governments/&#34;&gt;GFRC&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Municipal Fragmentation in U.S. Metro Areas in 3 Maps</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/16/municipal-fragmentation-in-u.s.-metro-areas-in-3-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 15:52:02 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2021/04/16/municipal-fragmentation-in-u.s.-metro-areas-in-3-maps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over on Twitter, Dan Immergluck (GSU) asked about what municipal fragmentation in the U.S. at the metropolitan level looked like. I, an expert on local government fragmentation, saw it as my duty to get to the bottom of this. I have the data to do it. It only needs to be reworked slightly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, it matters which CBSAs you include in how the map (and rankings) look. This is obvious but essential. Including the smaller CBSAs (50,000 to 250,000 in population) leads to many of these smaller areas dominating the rankings, largely in the Upper Midwest and Plains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/munifrag-ragg.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Municipal fragmentation, 2017, all CBSAs&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limiting the sample of CBSAs to those larger than 250,000 changes things slightly, with the center of gravity moving south and east somewhat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/munifrag-250k-ragg.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Municipal fragmentation, 2017, CBSAs larger than 250,000&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, constraining the sample to only those CBSAs larger than 1,000,000 in population gives the prototypical ranking with Pittsburgh and St. Louis at the top of the list. Generally, the most fragmented CBSAs are located in Rust Belt areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/munifrag-1m-ragg.png&#34;
         alt=&#34;Municipal fragmentation, 2017, CBSAs larger than 1,000,000&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;H/T to Andrew Rumbach (TAMU) for suggesting these maps needed a permanent home (more permanent than Twitter).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Symposium on Special District Management</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/10/03/symposium-on-special-district-management/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 14:47:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/10/03/symposium-on-special-district-management/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://paq.spaef.org&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public Administration Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is seeking papers for a symposium on special district management, edited by myself and Alex Henderson at Marist. You can find the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/paq-cfp-2020.pdf&#34;&gt;full CfP&lt;/a&gt; below. Abstracts are due on &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;. Selected manuscripts are due for peer review on May 1, 2021 and &lt;em&gt;PAQ&lt;/em&gt; expects publication in late 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;symposium-overview&#34;&gt;Symposium Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special districts are a profoundly important form of government, having experienced significant growth of the last several decades (U.S. Census Bureau, 2019). Though generally receiving less attention then general local governments, including cities, towns, townships, or villages, special districts are often charged with providing core public services that impact the day-to-day lives of citizens (Foster, 1997). These services include common functions like education, fire protection and emergency medical services, and library, water, and sewer services. Special districts are unique in their single functional focus, potentially complex and overlapping geographical boundaries that may not be conterminous with other units of local government (Bollens, 1957), and in the churning that comes through special district creation and dissolution (Goodman &amp;amp; Leland, 2012). Despite the growth and prevalence of special districts, our knowledge of these units of government is still relatively limited (Goodman &amp;amp; Leland, 2019), and additional attention to the management, functions, and contexts of special districts will add to the growing body of information on these important service providers. This symposium will provide a venue for conceptual or empirical research that examines issues related to the management of special districts. Topics may include, but are not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Management of special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Design and implementation of best / better practices related to managing special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Special district size, function, and interrelationships with local demographic, socioeconomic, or economic contexts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency and accountability in special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Performance measurement, program evaluation, and values of efficiency, effectiveness, or equity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Geography, local government capacity, and special district functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fragmentation among units of local government and service efficiency and effectiveness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other topics as related to independent or dependent (subordinate) special districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;proposal-submission-process-and-timeline&#34;&gt;Proposal Submission Process and Timeline&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This area of inquiry is necessarily interdisciplinary, and proposals from a variety of fields and specializations are encouraged. These may include those that focus on public management, urban planning, urban affairs, economics, and others. A 500-word proposal should be submitted via email to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:alexander.henderson@marist.edu&#34;&gt;alexander.henderson@marist.edu&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;strong&gt;November 15, 2020&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposals should include information on the purpose or aim of the article, a discussion of the methods or approach used, and a discussion of the fit with the symposium topic. Please also include author name(s), affiliation(s), and full contact information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proposal acceptance will be sent by December 1, 2020. Full manuscripts will be due by May 1, 2021 for peer review. Final decision on manuscript acceptance is anticipated by November 1, 2021, with publication in late 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CfP (PDF)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cgoodman.com/files/misc/paq-cfp-2020.pdf&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;CfP (Google Drive)&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1oHpDOBsEe4lbXWZwpysCi3mvTMdDBERx/view&#34;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bollens, J. C. (1957). &lt;em&gt;Special district governments in the United States.&lt;/em&gt; Berkeley: University of California Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foster, K. A. (1997). &lt;em&gt;The political economy of special-purpose government.&lt;/em&gt; Washington, DC: Georgetown University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodman, C. B., &amp;amp; Leland, S. M. (2019). Do cities and counties attempt to circumvent changes in their autonomy by creating special districts?. &lt;em&gt;The American Review of Public Administration&lt;/em&gt;, 49(2), 203-217.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goodman, C. B., &amp;amp; Leland, S. M. (2012). Cost shocks and their relationship to the creation, consolidation and dissolution of US local governments. &lt;em&gt;Public Finance and Management&lt;/em&gt;, 13, 58-79.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;U.S. Census Bureau. (2019). &lt;em&gt;2017 census of governments, individual state descriptions.&lt;/em&gt; Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Price of Residential Street Parking</title>
      <link>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/09/15/the-price-of-residential-street-parking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2020 11:38:02 -0500</pubDate>
      <author>Christopher B. Goodman</author>
      <guid>https://www.cgoodman.com/blog/archives/2020/09/15/the-price-of-residential-street-parking/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cities, broadly, manage a number of public assets with which they provide public services. Some of those services are somewhat passive in the sense that no active labor aside from maintenance is being carried out. And others are more active in that the asset is being used by public sector employees or contractors to provide a public service. We generally think of the latter as the primary mode of public service delivery as it is more visible. We see the bus driver, the police officer, the firefighter, etc in our communities doing their jobs. But the passive service is no less important. We drive on roads, use water and sewer infrastructure (though this is a blended service), etc on a daily basis as we go about our lives. One of the big differences between these two kinds of services is how the public sector asks users to pay for them. Some services are supported through taxes, but a great many are supported through user fees. Below, I point out two approaches to this for getting around a central city: the cost of storing a vehicle on a public street versus the cost of using the transit system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I choose these two the compare because they are roughly equivalent in their purpose (charging for the use of a public asset, roads v. a transit system), but the mode is different. Undoubtedly, there are private costs here as well. Car owners bear many costs associated with car ownership. Transit riders bear some private costs, mostly in their time, in using the transit system. But what we ask these two user groups to pay for the usage of a public asset is vastly different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is the monthly cost of a residential parking permit&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; versus the cost of a monthly transit pass for the 30 largest U.S. cities. In nearly every large U.S. city, on-street, residential parking is essentially free. If these residents were to park in a private lot/garage/space (i.e. likely much closer to the market price for parking), it could be many hundreds of dollars per month in parking fees. This suggests the usage of this public asset is being severely underpriced. Meanwhile, public transit passes are significantly more expensive. In many cases, the monthly cost of a residential parking permit is less than a single fare on the central city transit system! While likely not covering the entire cost of public transit, the monthly transit pass is likely covering a much larger proportion of the per user cost of the transit system. It&amp;rsquo;s highly unlikely this is the case for street parking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Pop. Rank&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;City&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;2017 Population&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Monthly Street Parking Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Monthly Transit Pass Cost&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New York City, NY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8622698&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$127.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles, CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3999759&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Chicago, IL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2716450&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$105.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Houston, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2312717&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$90.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Phoenix, AZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1626078&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$64.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Philadelphia, PA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1580863&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$96.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Antonio, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1511946&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$38.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Diego, CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1419516&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0.75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$72.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Dallas, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1341075&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0.54&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$96.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Jose, CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1035317&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$90.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Austin, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;950715&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.35&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$41.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Jacksonville, FL&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;892062&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$65.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;San Francisco, CA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;884363&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$12.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$81.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Columbus, OH&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;879170&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.08&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$62.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fort Worth, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;874168&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$80.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Indianapolis, IN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;863002&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$60.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Charlotte, NC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;859035&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.50&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$88.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Seattle, WA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;724745&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$5.42&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$99.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Denver, CO&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;704621&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$114.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Washington, DC&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;693972&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$2.92&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$81.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Boston, MA&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;685094&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$90.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;El Paso, TX&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;683577&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$48.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Detroit, MI&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;673104&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$70.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;24&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Nashville, TN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;667560&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$0.83&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$65.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Memphis, TN&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;652236&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;?&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Portland, OR&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;647805&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$6.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;27&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Oklahoma City, OK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;643648&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$50.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Las Vegas, NV&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;641676&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$-&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$65.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Louisville, KY&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;621349&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$50.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Baltimore, MD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;611648&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$1.67&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;$74.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these times of municipal fiscal distress, it is important to consider the costs of providing public services. Since residential street parking is often free (or minimally priced), the cost of upkeep and maintenance of street falls on all taxpayers through general taxation (usually the property tax). This is highly inequitable to non-street parking users who are asked to bear a portion of the cost while receiving no benefits.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The public sector asks transit users to bear a much larger portion of the costs associated with their usage of the public transit infrastructure than car users are asked to bear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residential street parking could be a decent revenue source for large cities. Vast sums of money are spent on the provision and maintenance of roads and few mechanisms exist to explicitly capture revenues associated with the usage of roads.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Appropriately pricing residential street parking could do this in a direct way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;tl;dr: Street parking in nearly all U.S. cities is vastly underpriced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that in many of these cities the residential parking permit system (or zones) do not cover the entire city. In a great many locations in these cities, street parking is essentially free (or uncharged for by the public sector).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t consider the social costs imposed either.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disconnect between the provision of roads and the revenues to pay for them is and will get worse as the efficiency of the gas tax (the connection between the amount of the tax and the usage of roads) further declines. This is driven by both the failure of the gas tax to be increased (most specifically at the federal level, but also in a number of states) and, paradoxically, the increased popularity of electric or hybrid vehicles that can avoid some or all of the gas tax&amp;rsquo;s intended purpose as a fee on road usage.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
